American Eugenics Society Records 1916-1973 Mss.575.06.Am3
American Philosophical Society
- Series I. Correspondence and Records (Box 1-20)
  - Osborn, Frederick (Box 17-18)
    - Frederick Osborn Papers, 1928-1971; 27 folders (178 items) (Box 17)
      - Involving the Whole Community in Education for Personal and Family Living, December 22, 1954; 13p. (Box 17, Folder 16)
      - Education for Personal and Family Living, March 1955; 4p. (Box 17, Folder 16)
        Published version from Eugenics Quarterly 2 (1955): 46-50
      - Population Quality-Women's City Club, April 1, 1955; 11p., draft (Box 17, Folder 17)
      - Make-up of the Healthy Family, April 22, 1955; 12p., draft (Box 17, Folder 17)
      - Notes for talk at Women's City Club, April 29, 1955, April 27, 1955; 5p. (Box 17, Folder 18)
      - Summary of the Course on Population Pressures Presented by Mr. Frederick Osborn, Executive Vice-President of the Population Council, at the final session, Women's City Club of New York, May 6, 1955; 3p. (Box 17, Folder 18)
      - Genetic Aspects of Population Replacement-Tokyo Conference, Oct. 1955, October 1955; 18p. (Box 17, Folder 18)
      - Galton and Mid-Century Eugenics, April 1956; 23p. (Box 17, Folder 18)
        Also published version from Eugenics Review 48 (1956): 15-22.
      - Changing Demographic Trends of Interest to Population Genetics, 1956; 15p. (Box 17, Folder 19)
        Also includes published version from Acta Genetica Statistica Medica 6 (1956/57): 354-362
      - Selected Publication of Frederick Osborn, [1956?]; 1p. (Box 17, Folder 19)
      - Inevitable Enlargement of the Field of Demography, April 25, 1959; 6p., plus abstract (Box 17, Folder 19)
      - Population and the Progress of Civilization, December 22, 1959; 5p. (Box 17, Folder 19)
      - This crowded world, July 6, 1960; 33p. (Box 18, Folder 20)
        Includes published version.
      - Qualitative Aspects of Population Control: Eugenics and Euthenics, Summer 1960; 34p. (Box 18, Folder 20)
        Includes printed version from Symposium on Population Control
      - Population pressuers and genetics, July 18, 1961; 15p. (Box 18, Folder 21)
      - A Return to the principles of natural selection, [1961]; 7p. (Box 18, Folder 21)
        Published version.
      - Absolute weapons -- The American reply, 1961; 9p., copy (Box 18, Folder 21)
      - Prospects for the evolution of personality traits, November 1962; 25p. (Box 18, Folder 22)
      - Excess and unwanted fertility, April 1963; 38p. (Box 18, Folder 23)
        Includes published version from Eugenics Quarterly 10 (1963): 59-72.
      - Eugenics and the races of man, September 1963; 6p. (Box 18, Folder 23)
        Published version from Eugenics Quarterly 10 (1963): 103-109.
      - The United States and the world population crisus -- American Assembly, Boston, April 1964, April 16, 1964; 19p. (Box 18, Folder 24)
      - The world crisis in population growth, September 1964; 17p. (Box 18, Folder 24)
        Published version from Clinical Obstetrics and Gynecology 7 (1964): 753-770
      - The human future from Science News Letter, July 25, 1964; 15p. (Box 18, Folder 24)
        Published version from Science News Letter 86 (1964): 49-64
      - Eugenics from Encyclopedia Britannica, October 1, 1964; 31p. (Box 18, Folder 24)
        Includes published version from Eugenics Quarterly 13, 2 (1966): 155-164
      - Crises of my times -- Introduction to war, bombs, and people, 1964; 11p. (Box 18, Folder 25)
      - The protection and improvement of our genetic ineheritance, 1964; 14p. (Box 18, Folder 25)
        With reprint from "The Population Crisis and the Use of World Resources"
      - Selection and survival in the industrialized United States, 1900 to date (Chapter 3), [1964?]; 20p. (Box 18, Folder 25)
      - Heredity and the Nature of Man, by Theodosius Dobzhansky -- Review, June 7, 1965; 3p. (Box 18, Folder 26)
      - The eugenic approach to population problems, October 1965, October 15-16, 1965; 13p. (Box 18, Folder 26)
      - Biological Aspects of Social Problems -- A review from Eugenics Review, December 1965; 8p. (Box 18, Folder 26)
        Includes published version from Eugenics Review 57 (1965): 182-184.
      - Covers and review "Future of Human Heredity" 1968, 3p., d.j. (Box 18, Folder 26)
      - The Eugenic Hypothesis. Paper for Symposium on Evolution, 1971, November 20, 1971; 26p. (Box 18, Folder 27)
      - Six year report, American Eugenics Society, 1965-1970., 1971; 15p. (Box 18, Folder 27)
    - Letters on Eugenics (Box 18)
    - See American Eugenics Society - Archives (Box 18)
  - Osborn, Henry Fairfield (Box 18)
  - Osborne, Richard (Box 18)
  - Osburn, Raymond E. (Box 18)
  - Osgood, Phillips Endecott, 1926 (Box 18)
    First prize sermon on eugenics.
  - Ostrander, Herman (Box 18)
  - Overlook, M. G. (Box 18)
  - Overstreet, Charles A. (Box 18)
  - Ownbey, Richard L. (Box 18)
  - Paine, Harlan L. (Box 18)
  - Parks, Mrs. J. B. (Box 18)
  - Pearce J. E. (Box 18)
  - Pearl, Raymond (Box 18)
  - Peckham, William C., in re (Box 18)
  - Pedigree Chart (Pratt family) -- See end of collection (Box 18)
  - Pellenberg, Emil (Box 18)
  - Pengilly, Richard, 1927 (Box 18)
  - Pennock, Edward A., in re (Box 18)
  - Pennsylvania Public Charities Association (Box 18)
  - Perkins, H. F. (Box 18)
  - Philanthropy (Box 18)
  - Philip, William Anderson (Box 18)
  - Pioneer Fund - Foundation Grant to AES (Box 18)
  - Pittenger, Mrs. O. M. (Box 18)
  - Pomeroy, Fred E. (Box 18)
  - Pope Pius XII (Box 18)
  - Popenoe, Paul (Box 18)
  - Population Council, 1951-1973; 108.0 Item(s) (Box 18)
    American Eugenics Society; Business; Conferences and symposia; Research support; Scientific organizations, meetings, programs -- Population Council; Solicitations for support or contribution
    - Grants to AES, 4 folders (Box 18)
    - Grant to Carl Jay Bajema (Box 18)
    - Program in Genetics, 1964-1966; 2 folders (Box 18)
  - Population Reference Bureau, Inc. (Box 18)
  - Poteat, W. L. (Box 19)
  - Potter, Ellen (Box 19)
  - Pratt, John T. (Box 19)
  - Pratt, William M. (Box 19)
  - (Pratt family), Pedigree Chart -- See end of collection (Box 19)
  - Project Talent, 1967-1969; 3 folders (18 items) (Box 19)
    Includes 3 copies of Carl Jay Bajema TMs, "Assortative mating: A research proposal utilizing Project Talent data."
    American Eugenics Society; Committee activities; Human genetics; Population genetics; Research support -- Bajema, Carl Jay
  - Purinton, D. B. (Box 19)
  - Purinton, Edward Earle (Box 19)
  - Ratliff, T. A. (Box 19)
  - Reese, Albert M. (Box 19)
  - Reid, S. Leslie (Box 19)
  - Rhodes, Robert C. (Box 19)
  - Richardson, James P. (Box 19)
  - Rice, Thurman B. (Box 19)
  - Risk, James K. (Box 19)
  - Robbins, Frank Egleston (Box 19)
  - Robert Burns Memorial Foundation (Box 19)
  - Robinson, B. F. (Box 19)
  - Roesch, George F. (Box 19)
  - Root, William T. (Box 19)
  - Ross, E. A. (Box 19)
  - Ross, H. E. (Box 19)
  - Roulston, Warren (Box 19)
  - Ruggles, Arthur H. (Box 19)
  - Rutland County Agricultural Society (Box 19)
  - Ryan, Arthur C. (Box 19)
  - Sands, Edwin H. (Box 19)
  - Population Study Proposal, Sanghvi, Lalit D. (Box 19)
  - Scanlon, in re (Box 19)
  - Schwartz, Emil and Son, Inc. (Box 19)
  - Scripps Foundation for Research in Population Problems (Box 19)
  - Sears, Benjamin F. (Box 19)
  - Selly, J. P. (Box 19)
  - Sessions, Kenosha (Box 19)
  - Settle, Anna H. (Box 19)
  - Shaner, Ralph F. (Box 19)
  - Shanks, Mrs. W. H. (Box 19)
  - Sharp, L. J. (Box 19)
  - Sherwood, George H. (Box 19)
    2nd International Congress of Eugenics. Executive Committee
  - Showerman, Grant (Box 19)
  - Shull, A. Franklin (Box 19)
  - Shull, George H. (Box 19)
  - Shutesbury-Leverett Survey, 1915-1928; 11 folders (Box 19)
    American Eugenics Society; Biographical and personal data; Eugenics; Human genetics -- Pedigrees; Maps; Photographs
    - Shutesbury-Leverett Survey, 3 folders (Box 19)
    - Card File -- See end of collection (Box 19)
    - Genealogical Data, 5 folders (Box 19)
    - Maps (Box 19)
    - Photographs (Box 19)
      For other photos see card file box.
  - Simmons, Daniel Monroe, 1926 (Box 19)
  - Slate Rock Farm (Box 19)
  - Slaten, A. Wakefield, 1927 (Box 19)
    Unitarian sermon on eugenics.
  - Sloan, Alfred P. Foundation (Box 19)
  - Smiley, James L., 1926 (Box 19)
    Episcopalian sermon on eugenics.
  - Smith, Arthur W. (Box 19)
    Shutesbury-Leverett Survey
  - Smith, Edgar B. (Box 19)
  - Smyth, Fred H. (Box 19)
    2nd International Congress of Eugenics Executive Committee
  - Social Biology Mailing List (Box 20)
  - Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children (Box 20)
  - Society for the Study of Social Biology, 1972-1974; 4 folders (Box 20)
    American Eugenics Society; Business -- Newsletters; Scientific organizations, meetings, programs -- Society for the Study of Social Biology
    - Financial Statement (Box 20)
    - Legal (Box 20)
    - Minutes (Box 20)
    - Newsletter (Box 20)
  - Southworth's (Box 20)
  - Spillers, Mrs. C. G. (Box 20)
  - Sprague, Robert J. (Box 20)
  - Stafford Springs Agricultural Society (Box 20)
  - Stamm, Frederick K. (Box 20)
  - Stanley, George L. (Box 20)
  - Stewart, Colin C. (Box 20)
  - Stewart, R. A. (Box 20)
  - Stockard, Charles R. (Box 20)
  - Stockwell, F. Olin, 1926 (Box 20)
    Methodist sermon on eugenics (third prize).
  - Stone, C. W. (Box 20)
  - Stoops, J. D., 1926 (Box 20)
  - Storrs Agricultural Experimentation Station (Box 20)
  - Sullivan, George M. (Box 20)
  - Tegarden, J. B. Hollis, 1926 (Box 20)
  - Thompson, Charles E. (Box 20)
  - Thompson, W. P. (Box 20)
  - Tillinghast, C. E. (Box 20)
  - Titus, E. G. (Box 20)
  - Todd, T. Wingate (Box 20)
  - Toll, Henry Wolcott (Box 20)
  - Trent, Issac N. (Box 20)
  - Tucker, Beverly D. (Box 20)
  - Tucker, E. B. (Box 20)
  - Turner, Willard J. (Box 20)
  - Tuttle, Charles E. (Box 20)
  - Tuxbury, Charles (Box 20)
  - Tyler (Box 20)
  - United States. Consulate. Nova Scotia (Box 20)
  - United States. Embassy. Japan (Box 20)
  - University Microfilms (Box 20)
  - University of Alberta (Box 20)
  - University of Arizona (Box 20)
  - Upham, Alfred H. (Box 20)
  - Upham, J. H. J. (Box 20)
  - Valley Fair (Box 20)
  - Van Nuys, W. C. (Box 20)
  - Vermont Industrial School (Box 20)
  - Vickers, Enoch H. (Box 20)
  - Voelker, Paul F. (Box 20)
  - Wagner, H. N., 1926 (Box 20)
  - Walter, Herbert E. (Box 20)
  - Ward, Mrs. C. F. (Box 20)
  - Ward, Robert DeC. (Box 20)
  - Waterman, Joseph MacNaughton, 1926 (Box 20)
    Church of the Resurrection sermon on eugenics.
  - Wellington, Charles (Box 20)
  - Wells, J. E. (Box 20)
  - Wheeler, George C. (Box 20)
  - White, Frederick M., 1926 (Box 20)
  - Whiting, Anna R. (Box 20)
  - Whitney, Charles P. (Box 20)
  - Whitney, David D. (Box 20)
  - Whitney, Leon Fradley (Box 20)
  - Whitney, Leon Fradley. Manuscript for book? -- See end of collection (Box 20)
  - Wicks, F. S. C. (Box 20)
  - Wiley, John and Sons, Inc. (Box 20)
  - Williams, J. M. (Box 20)
  - Wilson, Charles W. (Box 20)
  - Windsor County Fair, Inc. (Box 20)
  - Winton, W. M. (Box 20)
  - Wodsedalek, J. E. (Box 20)
  - Wolcott, Robert Henry (Box 20)
  - Wolfe, Mary M. (Box 20)
  - Womack, J. P. (Box 20)
  - Woodbury, Robert M. (Box 20)
  - Woods, Erville B. (Box 20)
  - Worden, C. J. (Box 20)
  - Wright, Sewall (Box 20)
  - Young, Howard Palmer (Box 20)
  - Zeleny, Charles (Box 20)
- Series II. Miscellaneous materials
  - American Eugenics Society Account Book, 1967-1972
  - American Eugenics Society Scrapbook, ca.1923-1929; 96 photoprints
    American Eugenics Society; Eugenics; Photographs
    - Alfred Mjoen in his library, n.d.; 1
    - Mrs. Mjoen in front of the laboratory, n.d.; 2
    - Mongolian idiots hands, 3
      Four boys, hands on white sheet
    - Mongolian idiots hands, 4
      Three boys from torso down, hands on knees
    - Dr. Harry H. Laughlin, n.d.; 5
      Board of Directors, Pres., 1928-29
    - Dr. Harry H. Laughlin with hat, n.d.; 6
    - William J. Hickson, n.d.; 7
    - Judge Harry Olson and Dr. William J. Hickson, seated, 8
    - Judge Harry Olson, n.d.; 9
    - Judge Harry Olson, n.d.; 10
    - Dr. Charles B. Davenport, ca.1929; 11
      Board of Directors to 1929
    - Judge Harry Olson, n.d.; 12
      Board of Directors
    - Prof. Henry P. Fairchild, Pres. 1929-30, Board of Directors, ca.1929; 13
    - Prof. Roswell H. Johnson, Pres. 1927-28, Board of Directors, ca.1927; 14
    - Dr. Jon Alfred Mjoen and Leon F. Whitney, 15
      Standing, arm in arm
    - Dr. Jon Alfred Mjoen lecturing on Mendelian inheritance, 16
    - Two young researchers in laboratory setting, n.d.; 17
    - Dr. Jon Alfred Mjoen pointing to stuffed rabbit, lecturing on inheritance, n.d.; 18
    - Dr. Fridtjof Mjoen and Heljar Mjoen in lab measuring ear length of stuffed rabbit, 19
    - Dr. Jon Alfred Mjoen, n.d.; 20
    - Man holding tail of rat, n.d.; 21
    - Two black guinea pigs, n.d.; 22
    - Four black guinea pigs, n.d.; 23
    - Two white guinea pigs, n.d.; 24
    - Two pairs of black guinea pigs, n.d.; 25
    - Two pairs of white guinea pigs, n.d.; 26
    - Pair of black guinea pigs, n.d.; 27
    - Pair of black guinea pigs, n.d.; 28
    - Three black, one white guinea pig, n.d.; 29
    - Pictures showing color inheritance in guinea pigs, n.d.; 30
    - Exhibit at Sesquicentennial Exposition, Philadelphia, Pa., 1926; 31
      Mendel's Theatre, Flashing light exhibit, and guinea pig board on display.
    - Eugenic and Health Exhibit, Kansas Free Fair, 1929; 32
    - Chart used at Kansas Free Fair showing "marriages fit and unfit" with outcomes of "pure" and "abnormal" unions, ca.1929; 33
    - Chart used at Kansas Free Fair describing "unfit human traits" and the importance of eugenic marriage, ca.1929; 34
    - Board showing color inheritance in guinea pigs, 1926; 35
      "Color Inheritage in Guinea Pigs"
    - Board showing color inheritance in guinea pigs, 1926; 36
    - Pointer dog, pointing, ca.1926; 37
    - Rough collie, ca.1926; 38
    - Pointer dog, pointing, ca.1926; 39
    - English bulldog, ca.1926; 40
    - Unidentified woman, n.d.; 41
    - Unidentified woman, n.d.; 42
    - Unidentified woman, n.d.; 43
    - Flashing light sign used with first exhibit at Fitter Families Contest, ca.1926; 44
      "Some people are born to be a burden on the rest -- Learn about heredity, You can help to correct these conditions"
    - Flashing light sign (Distant shot), ca.1926; 45
    - Mendel's Theatre showing inheritance of hair color, ca.1926; 46
    - Flashing light sign at Detroit (Sign in use at exhibition), n.d.; 47
    - Guinea pigs showing color inheritance (Guinea pigs in cages), n.d.; 48
    - Flashing light sign "Some People are Born to be a Burden on the Rest" used with small exhibit, 1926; 49
    - Flashing light sign "Learn about heredity, You can help to correct these conditions" used with small exhibit, 1926; 50
    - Mendel's Theatre showing inheritance of hair color, ca.1926; 51
      Leon Whitney demonstrating with pointer.
    - Examination building, Fitter Families Contest, Kansas Free Fair, ca.1925; 52
      Building at exhibit with sign: "Fitter Families for Future Firesides"
    - Eugenic and Health Exhibit, Fitter Families Contest, Kansas Free Fair, ca.1925; 53
      Audience in front of Eugenic and Health Exhibit
    - Eugenic and Health Exhibit, Fitter Families Contest, Kansas Free Fair, ca.1925; 54
    - Eugenics Building, Fitter Families Contest, Kansas Free Fair, ca.1925; 55
      Staff of Fitter Families Contest, Kansas Free Fair
    - Exhibit and Examination tent, Fitter Families Contest, Eastern States Exposition, ca. 1925; 56
      View of tent with sign, "Fitter Families Contest"
    - Exhibit and Examination tent, Fitter Families Contest, Eastern States Exposition, ca.1925; 57
      View of entrance to tent
    - Exhibit and Examination tent, Fitter Families Contest, Eastern States Exposition, ca.1925; 58
    - Interior of exhibit and examination tent, Fitter Families Contest, Eastern States Exposition, 59
      Man standing near row of cubicles with exhibit tags
    - Interior of exhibit and examination tent, Fitter Families Contest, Eastern States Exposition, 60
      People looking at papers near doorway labeled "History."
    - Two boys watching flashing light sign, n.d.; 61
    - Staff of Examiners, Fitter Families Contest, Michigan State Fair, ca.1925; 62
      Includes G. Van Amber Brown, Leon F. Whitney, and Mary T. Watts
    - Mr. Whitney, Mrs. Watts, Dr. Brown, n.d.; 63
    - Superintendent, Fitter Families Contest, Eastern States Exposition and Mrs. Watts, ca.1925; 64
    - Mrs. Mary T. Watts, Chairman, Committee on Popular Education to Dec. 1926. Died Dec. 1926, ca.1926; 65
    - Mrs. Mary T. Watts, n.d.; 66
    - Florence Brown Sherbon, Mary T. Watts, and Leon F. Whitney, 67
      In front of Eugenic exhibit building
    - G. Van Amber Brown, Supt. Fitter Families Contest, Michigan State Fair, n.d.; 68
    - Mr. Butterfield and Mr. Dickinson, Manager, Michigan State Fair, 69
    - Exhibit and Examination Building, Fitter Families Contest, Michigan State Fair, ca.1925; 70
      Front right view of building with sign: "Fitter Families Contest"
    - Exhibit and Examination Building, Fitter Families Contest, Michigan State Fair, ca.1925; 71
      Rear view of building
    - Exhibit and Examination Building, Fitter Families Contest, Michigan State Fair, ca. 1925; 72
      Side view of building
    - Exhibit and Examination Building, Fitter Families Contest, Michigan State Fair, ca.1925; 73
      Closer view of building with sign: "Fitter Families Contest"
    - Winner of Average Family class, Fitter Families Contest, Eastern States Exposition, 1925-26, ca.1925; 74
      Husband and wife, three boys, girl
    - Winner of Large Family Class, Fitter Families Contest, Eastern States Exposition, 1925; 75
      Parents and six children
    - Winner of Small Family class, Fitter Families Contest, Eastern States Exposition, 1925; 76
      Parents and two children
    - Winner of Large Family class, Arkansas State Fair, 1927; 77
      Parents and nine children
    - Winner of Large Family Class, Arkansas State Fair, 1925; 78
      Parents and fourteen children
    - Winner of Average Family Class, Arkansas State Fair, 1925; 79
      Parents and three children
    - Girl, "Ninth birthday", n.d.; 80
    - Mr. F. P. Snider, n.d.; 81
    - Mrs. F. P. Snider, n.d.; 82
    - Boy, "Eight years old", n.d.; 83
    - Winners in preliminary contest, 4-H Girls Club, Anderson Co., Iowa, 84
    - Winner of Large Family Class, Texas State Fair, 1925; 85
      Family posed in bathing suits, back to back
    - Winner of Large Family Class, Texas State Fair, seated formally, 1925; 86
      Parents and five children
    - Winner of Large Family Class, Texas State Fair, diving, 1925; 87
    - Winners of trophy for best couple, Texas State fair, 1925; 89
      Image was masked for newspaper publication
    - Family of Honorable mention, Large Family Class, Fitter Families Contest, Kansas Free Fair, 1923; 90
    - Winner of Large Family Class, Kansas Free Fair, 1925; 91
    - Fitter Family medal, "I have a goodly heritage", n.d.; 92
    - Winner of Small Family Class, Kansas Free Fair, 1927; 93
      Parents and son
    - Winner of Medium Family Class, Fitter Families Contest, Kansas Free Fair, 1927; 94
    - Winners of Small, Medium, and Large Family Classes, Fitter Families Contest, Kansas Free Fair, 1923; 95
    - Winner of Large Family trophy, Kansas Free Fair, ca.1923-1924; 96
    - Four Generations at Fitter Families Contest, Kansas Free Fair, 1923; 97
      Extended family depicted
    - Two pairs of guinea pigs, each consisting of a white and black guinea pig, 98
  - Shutesbury-Leverett Survey: Genealogical Data #1. Pedigree Chart (Pratt family), 1.0 Item(s)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
    OS
  - Shutesbury-Leverett Survey Card File
  - Whitney, Leon Fradley. Manuscript for book?